<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: unix | learn]]></title>
  <link href="http://goyalankit.github.io/notes-blog/blog/categories/unix/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://goyalankit.github.io/notes-blog/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-03T23:12:37-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://goyalankit.github.io/notes-blog/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ankit]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Unix Time-Sharing System Notes]]></title>
    <link href="http://goyalankit.github.io/notes-blog/blog/2014/09/03/the-unix-time-sharing-system-notes/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-03T00:19:07-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://goyalankit.github.io/notes-blog/blog/2014/09/03/the-unix-time-sharing-system-notes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>source</strong>: <a href="http://cm.bell-labs.com/cm/cs/who/dmr/cacm.html">http://cm.bell-labs.com/cm/cs/who/dmr/cacm.html</a><br/>
<strong>published</strong>: ACM 1974</p>

<h3>The File System</h3>

<p>From the user&rsquo;s point of view, three kinds of files:</p>

<ol>
<li><strong>ordinary disk files</strong> - no particular structure expected by system. Structure of files is controlled by programs (object files generated by assembler). Could be binary files or simple text files.</li>
<li><strong>directories</strong> - mapping between the names of files and the files themselves.

<ul>
<li>System maintains several directories for its own use.

<ul>
<li><strong>root directory</strong>: the starting point for other files in the system.</li>
<li>directory that contains commands to be executed. (not required, for convinience since commands can be placed anywhere).</li>
<li>null filename refers to current directory.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>A non-directory file may appear in several other directories under different names. - <strong>linking</strong>

<ul>
<li>A directory entry for this file is called a <strong>link</strong></li>
<li><strong>Hard Links</strong>: <code>ln file1 file2</code> - file2 now links to file1. Both file1 and file2 have same status. File doesn&rsquo;t exist in any directory in general, the directory entry contains link between filename and a pointer to the information describing the file.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Each directory has atleast two enteries with name &lsquo;.&rsquo; and &lsquo;..&rsquo; referring to current and parent directories resp.</li>
<li>The directory structure is constrained to have a rooted tree structure.</li>
<li>Cycles are not allowed in the file system. However Kernel mainains two restricted types of cycles in each directory: <code>.</code> and <code>..</code></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>special files</strong>: Each I/O device supported by UNIX is associated with at least one such file. Special files are read and written just like ordinary files. However, request to these files leads to activation of the associated device. An entry for each special devices exists in <code>/dev</code>.</li>
</ol>


<h3>Removable File Systems</h3>

<p>It is not necessary that the entire file system hierarchy reside on this device.</p>

<p><code>mount</code> causes the heretofore ordinary file to refer instead to the root directory of the file system on the removable volume. In effect, mount replaces a leaf of the hierarchy tree by a whole new subtree.</p>

<ul>
<li>No link may exist between one file system hierarchy and another.</li>
<li><strong>&lsquo;..&rsquo;</strong> refers to the directory itself instead to its parent.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Protection</h3>

<ol>
<li>Each user is assigned a unique user identification number. When a file is created it is marked with the user ID of the owner.</li>
<li>10 bits are used. 9 bits are used for R/W/X for self, group and others.</li>
<li>if the 10th bit is on, the system will temporarily change the user ID to the user ID of the user that created the file.</li>
</ol>


<h3>I/O Calls</h3>

<ol>
<li>There is no distinction between random and sequential I/O, nor is any logical record size imposed by system.</li>
<li>The size of the ordinary file is determined by the highest byte written on it; no predetermination of the size of a file is necessary or possible.</li>
<li>open / create system calls opens / creates file. There are no user-visible locks in the file system, nor is there any restriction on the number of users who may have a file open for reading or writing. The text may be scrambled if multiple users are writing at the same time.</li>
<li>System has sufficient interlocks present internally to maintain the logical consistency of the file system when two users are writing on same file, creating files in the same directory or deleting each other&rsquo;s open files.</li>
</ol>


<h3>Implementation of the File System</h3>

<pre><code>Directory:
  filename -&gt; pointer to file info [called i-number]
</code></pre>

<p>When a file is accessed, it&rsquo;s <strong>i-number</strong> is used as an index into a system table (the <strong>i-list</strong>)</p>

<pre><code>users/myfile

Directory: users
myfile -&gt; 4;

i-list (system table)
0 - i-node1
1 - i-node2
...
4 - i-node4
</code></pre>

<h4>i-node</h4>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
